[Music]
you say think is gonna happen hoping
that they don't happen hoping that by
virtue of saying and it's like a spell
and then it doesn't happen
well actually in our first
conversation you said something that
gave me the shivers he said like you
said like what happens if a million
people are you know die and we have to
watch that and what would the culture do
he said something like that
and that was like like a month before
this whole business came down and I
remember when you said that I you know
people say stuff and you don't you just
you just it just washes over you most of
the time but that kind of made me shiver
a little bit I remember that moment
to him I'm releasing the the one heaven
dialogue that three of us had tomorrow
on my channel so cool cool great yeah
well maybe we can we can delve in deeper
with the subject with the subjects that
we've already started to discuss you
know we are talking about we've already
started talking we talking about covet
and we've already started talking about
how this is a strange time a weird time
a bizarre time and and and the time
actually time itself is sort of
different during this period and which
is the Greek word Kairos that was my
first question that I had for you guys
is is if you could collaborate on this
this Kairos this idea of critical moment
sure you might have I go for a second so
is what's important to that I put some
fighting into that before all of this
when because in my series because I
originally got the notion from Tillich
and in
he talks about it in quite a bit of his
work and also connection you know it
took the courage to be and which he's
dealing with the meeting crisis and the
effect it's having on religion and his
time and of course it's he gets it he
has the Christian slant on it because
he's a Protestant theologian but and he
claims that it was that there was a
really interesting sort of Christian
spin on the Greek term one of the
original metaphor is not metaphorical
mythological in the good sense of myth
is the idea that of christ's advent came
in the fullness of time so the idea is
that systems will go along in place and
they have a lot of inertia to them
they're very resistant to change and
then certain sets of conditions will
console 8 such that an intervention will
have a huge has a huge potential to
really steer the course of things so the
idea about a Kairos is a fullness of
time in which timing matters because it
can turn the way in which time unfolds
so there's there's sort of many things
but that we're only in potentia have
come to a place where actualization and
transformation is possible and and so
the way I try to take that mythological
notion that mythological existential
notion because you you know you can note
you can note that in your own life you
do not like when you've been in a
relationship with person and you can
come to a point where you feel that you
know the relationship has been stable
and then it hits this point right at
hits this point and you go oh you know
this you know people talk about maker
breakpoints in in relationships and so
you get a sense that oh this this could
change the whole course of nature of the
relationship so there's that
mythological sense there's that personal
phenomenological sense and then I think
it I try to map it onto dynamical
systems and the idea of criticality in
self-organizing systems this comes from
per Bach
systems are self-organizing in
quite stable and then they get to a
point where the processes the very
processes that made them stable actually
start to undermine their structure the
classic example is the grain of you know
the column of stand that's falling and
it builds a mound and the mound is
stable for long periods and then when it
gets too high because of its
self-organization it goes critical it
avalanches its structure breaks down and
that criticality can either lead to the
disintegration of the system or it can
afford a new base from which something
new can emerge and be restructured and
so in my mind I sort of put those three
together when I think about Kairos and I
think we're getting increasing evidence
that we're in something I mean I think a
lot of stuff is already chaotic and then
I think the the the Cova crisis has just
been an accelerant of of the Kairos
Blair I yeah I mean I hold it similarly
I first got it actually from off table
Omar who was at Meridian University
whose students of James Helens work and
then read it read Hillman writing about
Kairos and relating it to this notion of
opportunity in particular and this is
kind of like penetrable opening within
the usually impenetrable fabric of fate
or time that there's like a nick in time
like in the nick of time in the sense if
there's a chink in the armor of Chronos
so that you can get in somehow and then
so there's something about it too and
relating it to the complex systems is
something that I do instinctively in the
in the realm of like individual
development that if you look at critical
periods in the development of any
individual the critical period of
adolescent identity formation for
example like most of adolescence feels
chyron ik it feels so much pregnant
opportunity so much can go right or
wrong and so much is locking in even
physiological the dysregulation and REE
regulation of whole parts of identity
structure but also
hormones and growth spurts and other
things similarly in early childhood when
you've got these critical the so called
critical periods which are they're not
set in stone but you can feel them when
they're happening as an educator or a
parent and they're kind of written into
the way the system develops and grows so
similar then you have a system that's
growing like embryologically for example
or developmentally epigenetically within
childhood
you're getting these periods of real dis
equilibration adolescence is a good
example where there's to be expected a
kind of identity dysregulation affective
dysregulation these things are kind of
par for the course there because the
system's trying to get up and into some
new form of patterning so crises are
usually moments of opportunity
they're usually these moments of Kairos
and identity crisis in particular when
you're thinking about the individual and
the kind of phenomenology of Kairos in
your own life like what's it like what
does it feel like you can remember those
periods in your life when it just you
were in it and so the question of kind
of antigen ontogeny recapitulates
phylogeny to what extent we can apply
that model to the growth of cultures and
civilizations we could say something
like you know the civilization is in a
kind of adolescent identity crisis of
hmm neurotic import which is to say like
this if we become a planetary
civilization this kind of pandemic is
something we're gonna have to be able to
deal with because of the nature of trade
and the nature of the travel and the
nature of their organization structures
it's kind of like this is what's like to
be a mature species that has planet eyes
like grow up we need to figure out how
to deal with this and so that's this
moment of opportunity where you're the
adolescent deals with reality or the
adolescent adapts to miss adapts to
reality and creates some identity
structure and behavior patterns that are
actually
adaptive and then you've locked in a
kind of a difficult way forward into
full maturation if not an end up being
self terminating identity construction
mmm-hmm so that's one way I kind of
model it I don't know if it's useful to
think about it that way
you know their limitations to it but
there's something powerful to yeah you
said that just you said that it's either
or either you go into a new higher level
of realization or the thing
disintegrates and when I was saying that
I think both kind of happens
simultaneously right it depends I mean
isn't that what sort of what's happening
now or what could be happening now or
well I mean it's may be that there's
there's a degree of the criticality
means the previous structure is
disintegrating literally to some degree
so but there is there is a there's a
tipping point right where if you go too
far the disintegration the entropy
overtakes the system and the system
collapses right and and and and you
might you might and and then it gets in
it can get stuck into a aberrant pattern
which is kind of like I think with
Jacques is talking about with the waking
goal become maladaptive you know like a
team you know who you know gets into
crime or something like that nothing
like that but there's a way there's a I
want to riff on with Jacques said
because so when you look at that those
that self-organizing criticality you can
actually see it in the brain you can
actually see it at work in the insight
like this is the work of stuff in in
Dixon in fact if when people are locked
into a frame and this is why maybe
bringing him framing might help because
we could sort of link framing an
identity that might give us even a
richer metaphor because they get locked
into a particular frame and then what
you have to do is you actually have to
you have to throw a lot of noise you
have to destabilize them you have to
introduce entropy into the system and
then that will actually provoke an
insight and what's interesting is you
can see development I mean I think you
did make a good argument
if from interpreting Piaget because he
sees the stages as bound to
systematicity of error you could see
development when you move from one stage
to another a systematic insight not just
an insight here or here but a much more
comprehensive set of insights like so
that your entire ways of looking at the
world entire ways of being would be
changing and that's where you could be
even see the cognitive change and the a
change in identity are then start to be
woven together and and why why that
might be helpful to think about it is we
sort of officially in terms of the text
books we're not we're not supposed to
call them critical periods anymore was
for because because the turn out the
term had that you know the you know if
you know if you're not exposed to
language by the time you're 12
you'll never get syntax and it had that
sort of so the the terminology doesn't
matter but it's felicitous here because
we now call them sensitive periods and
so the idea here is just like the noise
can sensitize the system and make it
possible for it insight and if you look
at complex systems you have sensitive
dependence on initial conditions when
you get into these Kairos States actions
that normally that would have just been
submerged into the system have like they
have a tremendous capacity the sense to
change the future course of the entire
system mmm and and so why I'm bringing
that up story this is a little bit
belated I'm trying to get the cognitive
and the the development of identity
linked to this notion of a special kind
of sensitivity because what that then
brings in that is that there's a timing
issue to this right there's a timing
issue to this that's really really
crucial so like an action that would it
have been impotent four weeks five weeks
ago yeah right now might make a big
difference and it might also be impotent
on five weeks from now right we're in
we're in a period where this
system is sensitive to our actions and
if we can figure out a system ax tissa T
in the air this is how I'm trying to
bring it all together we can make an
intervention that can permeate
promulgate throughout that entire
systematicity so it seems like if I
could just jump in that what we do right
now is very important
yeah it's what we do right now is very
important but we have to couple that to
a deep kind of discernment we have to
try and track out like is it in all of
the chaos and all of the noise is there
a systematicity of error signal we're
getting error signals this went wrong
this went wrong this went wrong this was
wrong they give up the kid is trapped in
conservation errors they're making
they're giving us all kinds of error
signals and then something happens in
their cognition where their brain
figures out oh wait these errors are all
related if I start doing this from now
on I won't make any of these mistakes
again we could do something analogous we
have to bring in there has to be like we
have to find that systematicity in the
error we have to find where we could do
so we can find like a nexus point right
so we can we can we can find what's it
sensitive to and where's the nexus point
and where can our actions make the most
impact right now so it's a timing it's a
timing it's a sensitivity issue it's an
issue but trying to find the
systematicity in the error I think the
people like we've got a we've got a
shift off of it's just chaos we've got a
shift - okay yes there's lots of noise
there's lots of entropy let's try and
find because if there's no systematicity
barrier we're screwed yeah there's no
systematicity error our interventions
won't make a systematic difference and
the system just gonna everything's just
going to collapse right and so it's it's
a timing issue it's the sensitivity
issue and most importantly it's a
discernment issue we've got to do a lot
of work to try and figure out what do
what what what what Gestalt what
Consulate's
all these error signals so that we get
some kind of unified sense of how we can
make use of the carros that's what I'm
trying to argue for mm-hmm
so let's do that maybe I did I think it
did um Zak
maybe Zak could riff on on this notion
of what
what how we can make use of this Kairos
because that seems to be the question
right is and you know what John speaking
to is exactly correct from my
perspective of thinking about
development and learning if you're in a
class and during the entire class you
get through you're never confused and
you're right like a perfect paper at the
end you have not learned that myself
right yeah well you i've always tell my
students like i want you to be very
confused at certain points and that
confusion is like a kind of Kairos
because you thought you understood and
now you've encountered something and how
you don't understand so you've been what
Piaget says disequilibrium right the
ability for you to just like run with it
is it no longer viable you have to
somehow adjust your operating and so if
you're in a situation you're trying to
develop or learn you need to be
comfortable with being just equilibrate
aroan off and put in this chaotic
confusion and then as johnny ii was not
saying within that you need to then
start looking for the invariants because
i'm going you're hunting that's what
Piaget was always looking for the the
abstraction of invariants from from the
environment and first you discover the
environment with your son the invariants
with your sensory motor properties and
the affordances of the body and then
slowly you extract the environs from the
social and the physical into these
abstractions and then into principles
and paradigms processes and some things
so there's something here there's an
opportunity for the social system itself
to move into a kind of higher order of
abstraction and complexity being able to
look at what's actually invariant
because when the simulation is going
it's not quite clear to tell what's real
and what's not real where's the
invariance like it's all working so when
you're perfectly equilibrating your
class and economics so it's making
perfect sense there's a good opportunity
that you're missing a huge part of
economics precisely because it's working
but there's something wrong there's
something missing they're just working
so well that you
can tell something's wrong it's working
so you can't tell something's wrong and
so this is what's been happening with
the civilization for a long time it's
been working so well for the key members
of the coalition yeah
yeah yep enough error signal it can
absorb it so exactly so it's absorbing
there so you know and so now there's
this thing where I now we're getting a
sense of all the possible error signals
and now is John saying we can look at
the system and today the error
systematicity of the errors and detect
the invariance and then that's the
opportunity to move to a higher order of
abstraction spelled reflective
abstraction in the pisciadood model and
then you have the grasp of consciousness
with the company is that so that's the
inside which is we put it in front of
you the subject becomes object as Keegan
says and then the grasp of consciousness
comes in there's insight and then you
can consolidate at the higher level
hopefully is that the other thing you
can have the insight and then drop back
down and this was a current Fisher's
great in stood like this movement of
this zone of proximal development the
development to arrange is such that you
can pop up and see it and then drop back
down let me hop up and see it again drop
back down so it's not just eating the
inside it's also finding the ways to get
the scaffolding in place to secure the
inside now kind of moving forward and
that's the level consolidation and so
then there's this notion of enduring in
transitional structures as part of the
developmental process that there are
some structures which are transients
they're put in place temporarily to get
to a structure that's actually an
enduring structure part of the learning
process like different kind of steps
that you can use you can have parts of
the web as fisher described in that's it
yesterday what structures are enduring
and what structures are sort of
superficial and are just treads
transition structures right and this is
the deep question and development you
know like there are some structures you
don't discard like the principles of
mathematics that you got from sensory
motor operation those are partyer
enduring cognitive structures but lower
levels of moral development often you do
kind of discard or at least you put them
in a different kind of
texts so yeah there's there's many
strands here but I pick up my general
yeah please
so one is to let's so what you just said
was very helpful because it helps me try
to refine this discernment that I'm
trying to put up because part of like
let's go back to the insight
problem-solving and one of the things
you do to get people to afford insight
as you call it you do the notice and
variance heuristic you get people to pay
attention and this is where why humility
is really important but you get people
to pay attention to failed problem
formulations and then you try to notice
what's invariant across those problem
formulations and then you change that
and that's exactly how you afford
insight so this this brings up a sort of
a question in my mind it's more of a
challenge to discernment which is how do
you you have to you have to you know you
have to notice the good in variants that
you're gonna track as you're talking
about exact but you also have to notice
the bad in variants that you have to let
go of but you have to abandon in order
to get the insight that is needed for
the transformation design there's sort
of part of the wisdom is what's the so
you get the noise we turn it into
systematicity as you said we're looking
for the invariance but I think there's
even something more fine-grain we have
to be able to discern the good
invariance if you'll allow me these
normative terms from the bad invariance
the bad invariants like that that might
be you know analogous to you know the
sets of constraints in the child schema
you know that was actually holding them
back and they have to be relaxed but as
you said that doesn't mean you abandon
all invariance because that's a disaster
and so it's not just it's not sorry I'm
not I'm not trying to be critical or
exact I'm trying to build on it it's not
just sort of finding the invariance it's
also finding it's also distinguishing
between the two kinds of invariants and
getting the right trade-off between them
I think is part of what we're also what
I'm also trying to get to with your help
to this notion of discernment that we
need to bring in did does that make
sense it does makes perfect sense yeah
and it's interesting that kind of
emotion and cognition er or completely
inter digitated
the Aegean model and so you get although
those works mostly are not translated so
he's conceived as a cognitive but it
always says that feeling emotion and
cognition they're related and so there's
a the the discernments not just
cognitive cuz you're right there's a lot
and there's a lot of invariants that we
don't own you know because it's not
relevant right because it's not part of
the of the field of what matters to the
developing child and so this is where
again I think also our identity and
cognition are related as well because
eventually what matters to me is a
function of who I take myself to be and
so in that sense this question of who
one is and how one feels which is to say
how one uses emotion as an information
system those are kind of like more
foundational than the cognitive moment
not more foundational but there's a very
deep interaction between these and you
can you cannot remove and this is what
makes AI so dangerous right is that if
you're removing the affective and
embodied vector of salience and
relevance let's say then your unmoored
from what actually matters and this is
that difference between the simulation
and the reality that civilizations going
to Sue's that if you're if the commodity
disguises its relation to the actual
biosphere so you don't realize that
actually this thing
it's the disembodied idea but the it's
actual body is quite dangerous
completely unsustainable couldn't be
extracted at that rate for another two
years five years you know depending on
what the commodity is and so there's
this way that though the cognitive
apparatus needs to be within the the
affective and the evaluative and I think
in baggage container when that helps get
the sense of which invariants am i
detecting right I agree with that
I mean fact I think that's fundamental
to relevance realization Montagu
actually talked about you know the
difference between us and computer
to use your your point azar is that we
have to take care of ourselves and
therefore we have to care about
information and so I'm using care here
in a high-tech gear sense that what
we're talkin relevance realization is
ultimately and I think this will get us
back to the affective stuff even the
existential stuff the you know like
you're talking about the level of
identity because relevance realization
is also ultimately processed by which
you're committing it's it's it is acts
of commitment and they could be micro
acts of committing no seconds of
attention seconds of arousal but it can
also be macro acts where you can you're
committing long periods of your very
precious and limited attention cognitive
resources time either so I I I think
that ultimately and this is what we
don't have to do the AI think but this
is one of the things holding back AI
right now because because ultimately
relevance realization is never cold
calculation it's never cold calculation
it's always an act of commitment and now
I'm gonna sound like Heidegger and
commitment is always an act of caring
and commitment and caring are always
identity forming processes that's just
the way I mean the best way to find out
who I am is not to do some sort of
romantic introspective act it's to pay
careful attention to what I
systematically care about that's that
that's that that's a clearer way of
getting at Who I am and what do I commit
to what what can you reliably hold me to
committing to well Donald Jonathan will
commit to this well that's the kind of
person John is and so I think I think
that if we could if we could agree that
you know this process we're talking
about is deeply one of caring and
commitment and cognition and I think
that overlaps with your terms of effect
and identity really deeply then is it
possible and and I like your point that
it's only that fully embodied process
that can get the discernment or at least
get good discernment between the bad
environments and the good invariants
what's the analog for the culture right
because I think you're right if we're
taking a look at an individual cognition
we can you know there's relevance
realization it's never cold calculation
it's you know it's about trying to zero
in on what I should care about what I
should commit to what I there by
identify with right and that that whole
process is you know and insight is just
moments where that's restructuring and
and that's what actually is helping me
pull apart the grid and variance from
the batted variance within times of
development times of Kairos so Zack this
is a hard question but I'm loving it
over to you what's the analog to
distributed cognition and collective
intelligence right it's a great question
the first thing that came to mind was
that something like a properly
functioning religion yeah try my best
not to buy away so I throw in one one
word here that I got from Nora Bateson
which came to mind you're talking he
talked about warm data versus cold data
is that what you're talking about like
warm data would be data that's embodied
and well I mean III got to talk to Nora
directly about this and there's a video
on my channel about that conversation
actually with 1010 Adaline and I think
any Nora means she means she's not
dismissing the effect but she's trying
to point out that we're all always if
you'll allow me this ethnographically
immersed and in the problems that really
matter to us they're not just sort of
problems out there there's there's we
are a complexity they're a complexity
and their interactions between them is
complex and so we the warm data is data
that is much more contextually sensitive
and comprehensive and more much more
dynamically sensitive and responsive to
that reality that's how I understood
what she meant by warm data I don't
think the effect part is being excluded
but I think I don't want to say that
that's what she's primarily put her in
your finger I think she's trying to put
a finger on yeah well no no there you
know there's the kind of data that we
are gathering when we're trying to do
the
important decisions the decisions that
involve commitment existential
commitment and transformation are warm
data decisions they're never data we can
never get data that is coldly dis
identified coldly abstracted and coldly
separate from us when we're trying to
wrestle on really important decisions
time that's how I understood her to mean
that okay well sorry Mike Chris John's
question I just threw that one but but
three seconds but I think that idea of
one data is exactly the kind of data
processing if you'll allow me to stretch
your metaphor that goes on in religion
so I don't think it's irrelevant what
you said Andrew I don't think it's great
yeah that's very interesting
yeah I'm out that's what times you get
Nagle's with the view from nowhere right
like this is the idea that actually no
it's not science its scientists there
everyone has a body and has a family and
mother who brought him forth screaming
and the dinner they go to the bathroom
and so the idea that the scientist is
primary that the science follows from
the scientists and you can take that too
far into the postmodern critique we're
all science becomes power and
psychoanalyze away truth and to Bob you
know biography but there is something
really profound about this reorientation
which has happened I think since the
maybe the 90s it's never been completed
that's not well distributed but there's
been an awareness of a lot of scholars
that actually we need to take the human
element within the knowing system very
seriously and that reduces us down not
reduces us but it it shifts the figure
in ground so that we become aware we
become more aware of the kind of
emotional identity positions that we're
in as researchers and and and
intellectuals and things of that nature
and yeah and so in that sense it's
similar to admitting that there are
religious aspects to even sign
right that we are investigating truth
together and that if we do it in an
earnest enough manner know that we would
end up finding things that we would kind
of live by and that would allow us as a
group to then do the kind of concern to
sermon you're talking about John like at
the cultural level there have to be
these shared frameworks of value and
identity and for shared frameworks of
reality and so that's interesting and
we've you know that cuts both ways right
we know the bad stories of religion and
we know my why modernity decided to try
a different way of organizing people and
it was important human evasion variance
right right Zak right like the stuff
it's not like you're not yeah when you
brought up you brought up the analogy
and say well what's that is for the
collective intelligence is a
well-functioning religion right then and
I want to really get to your previous
point I mean there's there's stuff we
shouldn't unlearned the fact that you're
practically if I can put it this way
you're not proposing religion in the
nostalgic fashion
you're not saying I want to give up this
is what I need this is you're doing it
right now you're trying to pull a part
right the the invariance that we should
hang on to from religion if you'll allow
me this language and discern which are
the what are the bad invariants that we
need to notice and let go of so we can
break through to a new developmental
stage I think you're you're doing
concretely exactly what I was asking for
yeah and this is the idea it's a
decentering and ph8 in terms and so
you're revealing you're moving out from
the surface to the depth and yeah it's
very interesting the notion of what are
the enduring structures that we need to
preserve within the traditions and
what's the form that the enduring
structures take is they're integrated
into new life structures emergent
structures and so the moment now the
chaotic moment is one where all the
structures are kind of coming undone
which means we can gather the bests
enduring structures together and move
them
yeah so that's that's an interesting
frame I like because this helps to make
beautiful to use a phrase from Plato 7th
letter the idea I was always rendering
very in a very ugly fashion I was trying
to talk about salvaging from these
traditions you know he tries to find
what was what's still good within which
which has been described but I like what
how we're talking about it now I think
it's much more refined and and much more
interesting so I guess so that has
something to do with the living beauty
you mentioned beauty right the living
beauty yeah I think what's what's there
rather than whatever is dog we're
superficial or or dangerous or that's an
excellent that's an excellent way that's
an excellent segue I do because I mean
so if you'll allow me to talk about a
bit you know UDL the aesthetics of this
are very important because the
aesthetics is precisely where we're
bridging you know between a lot of these
things what we Karen thing about it when
you when you're experiencing beauty this
is the great photonic insight you're
you're having one of your most profound
cognitive insight but you're also having
an education in the Platonic sense of
aware of your sensibility and what you
care about right this is why Plato
linked the understanding of beauty to
the cultivation of virtue and so think
about Ron's work on saving beauty and
think about the aesthetics so he he
talks about and you see how this is
pressing to a lot of ways before all of
this hit we were in what he calls the
aesthetics of the smooth we like things
that are smooth and you know like
objects that are smooth and and we like
data production and communication we
want everything to run smoothly and we
want everybody's face and the smooth is
a is an aesthetic that is the the
tyranny of the projection of the
subjective right the world is supposed
to be completely conducive to me and in
no way rupture or challenge me and what
he what he actually says and I think
he's right as he says we've really that
really has law
aesthetic is really lost beauty that's a
simulacrum of beauty rather than beauty
itself yeah which has always has edges
to it and and always is as depth and
even is a little slightly painful and
and well it should be performing and
yeah yeah exactly
brocade describes the angel beauty is a
terror that were basically barely able
and that's so much
um I think relevant right now because
you know beauty is something that's I
mean it should strike you that's the
verb that Plato uses repeatedly you're
struck by it it's and and the Greek is a
fairly violent striking right and and
the point about the lover and also the
fall-off Ilia Sophia the lover of wisdom
is the they have they have a capacity to
do well these affairs any in terms they
can find they can they can right
accommodate to the beauty and it's in
and they're not distinguished from each
other right the ability to accommodate
the beauty is precisely what makes it
beautiful if you can if you can't
accommodate you don't have you don't
have ah you have terror right mm-hmm and
so this this allows me to prim another
question right so think about the deep
interconnection of the education of
sensibility and aesthetics within a
religious community that's functioning
well here's how I think of you know
they're one of my friend and colleague
Jonathan Peres show where he goes back
and he tries to re-educate people right
into what all this symbolism was doing
you know aesthetically in this deeper
sense that I'm talking about seeing
seeing the the aesthetics of people's
experience as a fundamental thing sweep
okay I'll put it in a put it in a
sentence and I'll turn it to Zack as a
question
right I think you know children go
through this the little with serious
play I've made that argument before you
guys are familiar with it we can bring
it up again
but right I think and coupled
has to be an education that removes
aesthetics out of entertainment and puts
it back into education and and because
that's part that's a part of is a
religious vision that Zak I think is
alluding to that we have lost the threat
of we've lost the threat of in a
powerful way and so my question to zach
is that right do you think that so this
is kind of self-deprecating for all of
us as well do you think that the answer
that we're looking for and I don't mean
that as a simple answer you know what I
mean a comprehensive trustworthy
response is going to come out more from
an artistic set of people people that
are at home with the transformative
aspects of beauty then us intellectuals
so I'm getting a lot of emails from
artists now that I didn't I didn't get
before a lot a lot more and their dirt
they seem to be the people that rush
into the Kairos better than anybody else
because they one of the ways they
systematize the error is if you'll allow
me a verb a they beautify it which isn't
the same thing as resolving it and are
solving it in the intellectual fashion
but they beautify it so that people can
accommodate it and move into it I mean I
think what the answers gotta be of
course of course it's gonna come from
the artists you know I think Plato said
though that often the artist doesn't
know exactly what they're saying on but
they're saying the truth the more
profound truth than the intellectual
could say but they they don't know
exactly what they're saying because
there's an inspiration there's a muse
that gives them the insight and so can I
just agree maybe what they know is in
the future they have an insight that is
unpacked that hasn't been unpacked yet
so they have a prophetic as what I
wanted is prefer to gather the artist
accredited since which you can't really
access through mere intellectual idea
that the artist is prophetic
is I think it's actually one of the it's
kind of one of the unspoken kind of
Gospels of modernity actually is that
the artist is prophetic the only place
where the prophet still lives within the
kind of deep disenchanted nature of
modernity is in the artist they get to
be the kind of prophetic voice and
Emerson's poet comes to mind right for
Emerson the poet was much deeper for
Emerson the Pope was like Socrates was
the greatest poet Jesus was the greatest
poet right and so you end up getting
this notion that the artist is exactly
the person to live to and the german
idealists ended up here too with
romanticism and and they have their
attempts to create a kind of uber
christianity with all these symbolisms
moved also towards a kind of artist as
social reform on guard and then when you
look at artistic personality types from
a psychological perspective you also see
the sensitives and the people who are
aware of the war in heaven even as the
simulations going and everyone else is
trekked that the world to normal the
artists are usually clued in which is
why I hold artists usually it's actually
kind of a vulnerable population which is
to say they end up medicated or
institutionalized or addicted or
unemployed underemployed miss employed
so there's a noble Marge marginalize or
systematic the marginalized and
modernity writes that into the artists
that this is what you have to struggle
to mean I think I justify it but you
know other societies have revered their
prophets although they've been
persecuted but so yeah so I think
looking to the aesthetic and realizing
that although we can see the
intellectual synthesis clearly the way
for it to ground in the human heart is
going to come from something more like
an artistic movement and when you're
thinking of the move
I think of from entertainment to culture
right I think of the theater and I think
of the disappearance of the theater into
the movie
right now the potency and the
possibility of the movie to do what the
theater did for ancient Greece right and
to show us this complex cathartic
beautiful thing that allows us to be
people in a new way together like you
don't could do that but I've seen one
that's unhappy what I see is mostly an
industry which is capturing attention
and etc etc so yes part of this move out
of entertainment and into culture is
changing the incentive systems around
cultural production and so that means
moving the artists out of marginal into
something like supported right and
through either federal or private
reinvestment there's a serious thinking
now in this time of crisis when a whole
bunch of money is moving around for
better and for worse thinking about what
the hell's gonna happen of the artists
right what that was gonna happen to the
to the young yeah the yeah the people
who would give us those symbols and the
effective grounding point so we can move
around the answer that's kind of what's
coming up when I'm thinking what you
said John and I'm agreeing with you
enough to say well yeah we actually
attract that that's priority and figure
out in schools and colleges and cities
how we can support artists now it's
interesting problem this this this
connects to a lot of the things that I
actually wanted to talk to you guys
about and both both of you if have been
talking about stealing the culture I
think that was John's phrase and your
phrase Zak was your talk you talked
about being an outlaw right and being an
outlaw not in some kind of let's say
immature
adolescent you know rule-breaking sense
but being an outlaw and as the person
who breaks the rules so that the new
rule can emerge or the new culture can
emerge and maybe that's related somehow
to this prophetic artist
personality we're talking about Socrates
was eventually killed by the state and
so I think that's relevant and the
prophets no prophet what did Jesus say
no prophet is honored in his own home
what I'm interested in
it may be answering that question are
people like Socrates and especially
Plato but also platonist and people like
Barfield and you know courage and the
the early post content that Zack was
alluding to and good that comes to mind
as well um these are the individuals
right and it was interesting that when
Nietzsche pronounced he gave one clear
example that he stood behind as an
example of the uber mentioned it wasn't
Napoleon that wasn't Hegel it was good
the artist was good too but the thing
about Goethe and the thing about
Socrates right is you you baby
let's do at least Plato cuz Plato said
that he made Socrates more beautiful
let's take Plato because the the the if
you'll allow me the artistry and the
argumentation are completely
interpenetrating so the artistry and the
argumentation and the aspiration are all
deeply interwoven together like you
can't pull them apart like people you
know Zack probably had this too maybe
you did Andrew in my education when they
taught me Plato I was taught a great
disservice because what would they would
do is they would distract the arguments
out of the drama
remember the your reference to theaters
aren't it was right and they would and
they would not even bringing up it was
it was marginalized to obscurity the
aspiration all right so the artistry and
the aspiration were put aside dismissed
and then always held out is the
argumentation but I'm interested in
those kinds of people who can do it
because I think they I think they're
well I suspect I'm trying to be very car
sir I suspect that they're more
important than just the artist right now
I think the aesthetic is important and
the artists are going to be do a lot for
us but I think that
the those individuals who make great art
while also making new forms of thought
and new ways of being that so the three
together I think they're the individuals
and what's interesting for me is I've
been trying to pick up on how do they
communicate and how do they think with
and through other people right
the idea that dialectic is always this
deeply interpenetration of argumentation
aspiration and artistry and in which the
beauty and the truth seek this the
beauty seeking and the truth seeking and
the transformation seeking are all bound
up together and so I'm kind of looking
to see and so here's another hard
question for you is that because you've
been doing really well and answering
them feeling immiscible there no but I
can make it concrete how do how do we
educate for a good and this is the
question of Bill doing which is of
course sourced and that goes you know
Thomas Bjork when I had a conversation
with recently and he pointed to the
whole bill doing movement and this so
this is important because it's not you
TOEFL the bill during a movement is
anticipated in you know instituted in
the secular monastery retreats retreats
that Network in the Scandinavian
countries to turn them from an
authoritarian or grand societies into
some of the best most advanced and
happiest places on the earth so this is
not fantasy this is not utopia this is
doable it has been done there's a
historical case and Thomas worked in
order seek it lays it out really really
well
yeah and Goethe and Humboldt and yeah
the the immediate post Conti in milieu
it was that sense of and you're right to
correct me that it's the it's all three
it's the good deterring a beautiful
United and so complex symbol right and
that day yeah in our society someone
who's capable of doing that probably
looks more like an artist than the
scientists as Goethe did right but as
many people know Goethe was actually a
totally badass
scientists and this was real rough
Steiners many people don't know this
Rudolf Steiners first work was actually
in the archives of Goethe looking at his
scientific work and
there's a richness there but yeah so the
point being that yeah the what we're
looking for is that complex truly after
modern right to the the differentiation
of the value spheres separating art from
science from morality right the idea
that they need to be reintegrated in
some new form that's the that's the in a
sense the holy grail of of the of the
West that the only way out of this is
the somehow reintegrate these these
values fears and to somehow find forms
of expression and communication and
interaction that represent a new merger
of them not a regression back to the
medieval system where they were fused
together right where you couldn't get
that's their work because there's so
many you can't talk about the planets
because we already know because there's
so many orifices in this face that there
can't be some of it so like the dogmatic
don't look through the telescope Galileo
pre-modern undifferentiated than the
differentiated modernity and then Weber
lays out the problem right the
technocrats without hard and the
aesthetic artists without any sense of
ethics and the fragmentation of the
unity dimensional man and so always the
quest has been this reintegration and
one way to think about the problem is
actually also as a there's a
socio-economic thing here that in fact
we need to heal certain underlying
social structures to allow for those
forms of complex identity formation back
to the question of Education which is
where you're moving this because the
caricature of the artist right now is
some wounded degenerate tight who's kind
of an egomaniac and doesn't get along
with the rest of society and it's
narcissistic and and and the scientists
and the scientists the and he's got new
emotions and he might as well be a robot
right and the politician is cutthroat
and the businessman has no morals or
aesthetic sense and so that sense that
there's each person because this is
fragmented so can I say that maybe the
artist is actually the total person
right it's not it's not being an artist
as a specialized activity in a sense
being an artist is is what we're all
sort of the total person
meant to be on some level right whether
you actually art or not if we're using
artists in that sense that we were where
the artist is the one who finds a way to
make a life that reunites the fragmented
value spheres of modernity right that
that like I said the Emersonian poet who
integrates the good the true and the
beautiful if that's the artist talking
about then yes but again the the artists
of modernity right the mad genius like
derelict marginalized artist is as much
of a kind of character as the modern
businessman or the modern politician yes
also stopped from having aesthetic sense
or an ethical sense and so it's it's
just that sense again the whole person
where you can essentially not be
fragmented at such a root level
alongside clefts and identity as the
good deterrent the beautiful and I get
the sense that like when we were talking
the other day I mentioned poetry and
John kind of jumped and said no because
of the way people think of a poet today
it's there's this contempt for poetry
right and then maybe this event that's
happening right now when people are
stuck in their houses etc etc maybe they
will start to see a little bit like the
value of that of the poetic poetry are
oh I agree I think that crisis it does
two things and they play off against
each other
I mean it creates Dom aside it because
people connection it brings on
loneliness it puts them into this weird
and threatening you know almost demonic
you know world view and so in many ways
and we're already seeing this it
exacerbates the meaning crisis I predict
we're going to see a mental health
crisis shortly on the heels of this that
is going to also be Titanic and cause a
suffering and death but Pressley because
of that people are right also turning to
seeing how important meaning making is
not semantic meaning talking about me
in life meeting making the connectedness
but I want to I want to I want to bring
up so I think you're right that that's
part of the car Ross Andru but I want to
say that I think there Kairos and our
discussion is leading me to a deeper
question so that keeps giving these
great answers and then they can they
afford me going deeper and this may be
you know cycles back to Tillich and
maybe he cycles back to the good in
variants and the bad in variants because
whatever what I wanted to say think
about how we got here so I'm using
hammer mouse here think about how Kapaun
separated those three faculties in the
three critiques the tree Capital Region
judgment tried in practice he says
grateful right he separates them and
then Harbor of losses argument is part
of what drives that fragmentation is a
normativity of autonomy reason is
autonomous and therefore it cannot and
should not be integrated or reduced it's
in a sense even in commensurable from
right from morality which is then also
autonomous the right it is a tournament
and that's autonomous from taste
so the normativity of autonomy right arm
is for grounding and that is if you
allow me don't know that's an autonomy I
mean maybe Heidegger and my colleague my
Johannes Nina Hauser that that's that's
a Norman TV ultimately of subjectivity
self-governing autonomous right right
right it's it's ultimately a Cartesian
normativity yeah no I I am ultimately an
isolated right thing and itself and and
and mine or and the only normativity
upon me is my is my autonomy and all of
these do you see what I'm trying to get
out there's a normativity of autonomy
now Tillich in his worth tried to break
out of that he tried to say there's
three possible kinds of normativity
there's of course the normativity of
autonomy and that
is pervasive in the cognitive grammar of
modernity and then he said but there's
also of course the normativity I called
it heteronomy in which somebody is
imposing on us and this is a this is an
authoritarian of one form of another and
he was he was brilliant enough to see
how the Nazis were playing those two off
against each other when they I don't
want to bring up the Nazis very key it
this this analysis affording it came in
sight and then he proposed you'll see
where I'm going with this
he posts he those two he said what we
really need because the first emphasizes
subjectivity right autonomy the second
that localizes everything in objectivity
right but he said there's a third which
is the enemy and this is being god
governed right and and this brings us
back again to the well functioning
religion the idea is there are a certain
form because when people feel called by
God they don't feel that they're being
demonically possessed but they don't
feel like they're acting autonomously
they feel it's if they feel
simultaneously that they are moving
they're being moved by something beyond
themselves but they're also being moved
by something that is helping them to
realize themselves in an important way
and so I think part I think there's a
deep reason by and do why you brought
this up and I think it's even a deep
fear since you suck why you circle back
up well function religion like if we're
going to break out of the fragmentation
we have to challenge the normativity
that drives the fragmentation which is
the absolute value radiation of autonomy
as the final way in which all moment Eva
T is generated no that's not to give in
to hitter on ax me and say Oh what we
need is the strong man and the
authoritarian structure and Tillich was
really playing with the idea that what
Christianity was trying to offer people
was the animus um normativity and it
would break us out and we help to
reunite us as an entire person
well that's very abstract so that's
exactly what Zack was talking about when
when you talk about the unique self
Symphony I have it written down here in
a mystical body of Christ it's breaking
out modern idea of self right our modern
idea of self into something else you
call that sovereign self I'm not quite
sure I understand what I want to refine
I think that's what the back was that's
exactly Zacks yes concept and he also
you're also said that's the mystical
body of Christ right yes yeah right
that's not that's not the most
conventional way in but yes to
eventually is in one consistent the
mystical body of Christ and it was
interesting here is that we can go back
to the developmental theory because that
stack you just ran from heteronomous to
autonomous - what was it Theo the
Ottomans beyond the anima stright which
you can also think of it like theosis
only yeah and so that that stacks very
closely to the pre conventional
conventional post conventional way of
thinking about moral development which
is of course inspired by count through
Kohlberg and picked up by Hamas as part
of our bosses moral and political theory
and when you look at how our mosques
fear of democracy he's actually trying
to overcome the autonomously bastes
rationality of the subject of modernity
and get in its place not a Christianity
based notion of post conventionality but
a post conventionality nonetheless and
so you end up having a way of thinking
about moral development we're at the
higher reaches you get a a transcending
of the modern autonomous kind of like
subject and a relinquishing into
community and also into transcendence
people that realized Kolchak had a
famous comer had a famous 7th level like
he had a 6 6 stage model for his whole
career
but he ended up in a essay writing about
this 7th stage in the seventh stage the
exemplars were like Spinoza and Socrates
and teal er de chardin and Marcus
Aurelius and people who got all the way
up to the post conventional autonomy
that one would expect and then also gave
over the self and kind of Abraham has
those self-transcending kind of giving
over the self on the altar of the ideal
and and so that yeah that's a different
form of identity which allows for a
different kind of politics and a
different kind of art and science and
and everything but the task demands of
that are quite steep and this is like
one of the flaws and Harbor mosses fear
democracy between facts and norms is
this big thick book and the issue there
is that he's expecting all citizens to
be able to be post conventional in their
moral judgment and cognition and this is
very I mean this is where then you know
Dewey comes in right that education
democracy are like this that if you
going to have a kind of decentralized
sense making as a way of running it if
you really want to do that then you need
get everyone up through the educational
system to a very very high level of
complexity and identity formation
yes so we were at this notion that
there's yet preconventional conventional
host convention all that the challenging
the basis of the the root of the modern
form of normativity basically it's what
we were looking at and it has to do also
challenging the route of the modern
identity so the new form of new form of
normativity a new form of self Co emerge
yes Robert Brandon who's one of the
great philosophers of our time
University incredible work on the nature
of normativity and actually rehearsing
Hegel in a profound way is this great
section heading for his win one it was
his big book making explicit it says
we've met the norms and they are ours
this is just to say that you know one of
the things that makes the post
conventional identity post conventional
is that they're norming the norms that
the practice is not disobeying the norms
were not even understanding the norms
but understanding the norms and then
getting above that and be able to norm
the norms but norm the norms in by
virtue of what and now we're back to the
discernment in the Congress right which
is that you if you go post conventional
there's this delicate moment and
Kohlberg research which is that you've
critiqued the norms of society but you
haven't established a principled view of
your own so now you're supervening on
the norms of society critiquing
everything turning into a relativist and
the hedonist which is what happened a
lot in these transitions and you haven't
got found a discourse community of other
post conventional people that will allow
you to equilibrate in in principled way
and have a sovereign and a sovereign
notion or wave forward and so yeah so
that's funny educational challenges you
can only be a heretic if you found other
heretics or people yeah and this is the
dialogue Oaks balancing and other trends
your trends transcending that the norms
and bring it to a higher level and
moving between communication communities
so moving between identity structures is
often about moving between communication
communities and expanding your
communication community often to include
the mighty dead right like that you
don't have a local community where you
can talk the way you need to talk to be
who you are you need to expand and have
conversations with more and more and one
of the ways to ground post conventional
morality which is to say I'm not
appealing to my community about what's
right and wrong rather I'm appealing to
what George Herbert Mead called an ideal
communication community this is back to
the yellow he write that there's a
community in which I am a part of which
is not spatio-temporal located by which
I judge my behavior so it's not you guys
local community to to which I'm behold
and although I am because you're my
immediate neighbors but I'm holding to
this ideal
munication community which could be all
sentient beings if you wanted to pay so
there's something there too about how to
create contexts where post conventional
identities can be formed through
conversation and linked into the ideal
communication communities beyond the
local to have that sense of courage and
ancestry and all the things that
constitute identity which are hard to
come by if you're trapped in the local
conventional community and that won't
allow for your identity formation and so
much possibility of identity formation
has been opened up with a move out of
enduring meaning to post modernity ins
digital but we still haven't solidified
the die logos of actual identity
construction at the post commencement
level we're mostly critiquing and the
outside of the norms without having any
way to norm the norms with systematic
conversation and so they're back at post
conventional religion again or or we're
back at posts of conventional religion
but we're also and I think we're also
into
circling back to Piaget I think we're
going to post forum a lot where we're
not we don't just think within an
axiomatic system we know we learn how to
think between axiomatic systems and
that's one of these that each one of
these normativity sees itself as an
axiomatic system but we have to remember
we've got we've got a you know a really
profound truth that undermines that
which is no system is simultaneously
complete and consistent gdel the every
system has to have a doorway out of it
and you can't infer a stronger language
are stronger logic from a weaker logic
etc all these things that have told us
that the that then if our claims to
autonomy are ultimately not viable
because that autonomy can never have a
complete normativity because it will
always trade between consistency and
completeness if it tries to pursue Venus
you will start to give up and it's
consistency and then that make that
destabilizes it or if it tries to remain
consistent it then freezes
so it's these systems are always always
hovering between destabilization and
fixation and so that for me gives me
great hope but what I and I like the
invocation of the logos right diello
goes the way of the logos the logo says
that thing that's norming the norms I
like the way you put that song and what
I want to bring in it and this comes
from Tillich but it is ultimately due to
Heidegger is and it goes to both
Maslow's and on Kohlberg
self-transcendence right to think about
the logos is it has the life of its own
it's not it's not and it's not
abstractly independent from us but it's
it right it doesn't belong to us we
belong to it it takes on a life of its
own and here's the thing and not only it
not only right it is not only connected
to us it's also connected to the way
intelligibility and even reality are
unfolding and that that's ultimately I
think why we belong to it rather than if
belonging to us and so part of what I
think the sage artists can do is in is
invoke do logos and invoke that as you
know the thing the the sort of trans
systemic thing that allows us to bridge
between the normativity an important
length and I think the so I want to
throw in that one of the things that has
supported the autonomy and the
subjectivity you know model and and then
and then we have this thing called
authenticity which isn't part of your
sense it just basically means sort of
celebrating your autonomy right um but
one of one of the one of the things that
I'm trying to get at right is this idea
that in the dialog and in the dialectic
we have access to right a way like
when you swing you read when you read
the dialogues it's not just
argumentation that's in competition ways
of life are being brought into
competition but not just in an arbitrary
fashion that they're being regulated but
is that's the right word there being
regulated by the logos and everybody has
to be willing to follow the logos which
doesn't mean just drifting subjectively
it means you know answering the call
being responsive to the way it's taken
on a life of its own and that it's it's
polarity it is it's not grounded in us
it's grounded between us and each other
and the end our culture of
intelligibility and ultimately the world
in which that culture is embedded like
the logos the logos exemplifies the
normativity of our embeddedness and in
accent for us and I think that is a way
in which linked with sort of post
conventional thinking it can help us to
get the kind of Fionna --mess
normativity that I'm trying to talk
about the the you know well we talked
about this and Zack Zack as you use it
there's something sacred or perhaps even
divine about the logos that and that's
what I'm trying to get it to take the
role the Fiona the Fiona must roll that
till it was 20 towards did that make
sense I was struggling there did no I
mean it was it's a beautiful
international essentially if I'm hearing
us that this artists we've been talking
about this like Gertie and RDS who
integrates the value spheres what
they're creating there were there it's
like they're they're inviting us
actually to something into something
other virtual some kind of ritual of
interaction and communication where the
logos is revealed between us right yeah
the artist needs to create power
reflected yeah perform it's like a
performed that's why theater is so
interesting and a figure that would
break down that fourth wall and engage
the audience you know and so they're
always hints in postmodern art that
there was something trying to emerge
that would actually embrace the audience
and blur the line between the art and
non-art
though in essentially Reese Accra lies
all of life by casting the veil of art
across all things and so that notion
that the artists were looking for
someone who invites us into a new ritual
and way of being worth through it we
can't help but be swept into the logo
essentially and that were going full
circle into the logos mysticism right of
the the Western tradition rooted in the
Neoplatonic stuff and yet a sense that
there's a way to there's a way to create
a human civilization so I'm thinking
Thainess here in particular he he almost
built a city yes big anomalously yeah
exactly he must build a city and so he
was in this kind of civilizational
design mindset from a deeply meta
philosophical the Platonic view and so
my sense is that yeah in this such a
society there would be some kind of and
again when you think properly
functioning religion it's not just like
the books and stuff right it's like
there's a building and we all get there
and we're in it together and we do
something and what that something is is
a ritual that would be tremendously
beautiful and that would bend the
conception of it would be as you're
describing John it would be not us all
looking at one thing like some medieval
ritual but in fact this moving between
us of the Holy Spirit and of the
dialogue goes yeah where the evidence is
clear just by that were fact we're here
together looking one other's eyes and
that's what can happen sometimes that's
why a a works and that's why circling
works at a bunch of other things work
because you just it descends it's there
you're looking between the eyes there's
a self-evident value in the experience
of their personhood and co-relating and
it's funny it's like they always say
you're selling water by the well or
selling water by the river or something
like that like this is one of those
sayings you know and
that it's right there yeah and I likes
the idea that the logos is building
something like you said building a city
or a Patronus is building a city that
strikes me as that's the thing that is
building the city of God is the logos or
you know if we got in yeah
Craig turns there's two myths total
identification crisis identified with
the body of the church but Christ is
also identified with the logos of God
right and it's because I said because he
medias between them and he creates ways
of being
he was the followers of Christianity
were the followers of Jesus were
originally not called Christians that
was an insult they originally called
themselves followers of the way right
followers of the way of logos yeah this
way of being it exemplified rendered
beautiful to us attracts us it's
proleptic it inspires us to ask fire it
affords appreciation right it allows us
to be you know a postformal
allows us to be postconventional you
know these famous Augustine you know you
know learn how to love God and then do
whatever you want that the to be right
that the two are always bound together
that's faith again that's something to
do with faith isn't it well following
the logos you're following faith in a
way you're not following a kind of you
don't have a model it's not how to build
the thing you're following a third
element you are it depends on your
definition faith like circling or in a a
meeting or even these conversations here
yeah like I came into the conversation
with a survey that it was going to be a
good conversation I had no idea exactly
how it was gonna go but I knew given the
nature of reality in my experience with
all you guys that there was a sense that
it was going to work I don't know
exactly how this is like a micro example
it's not it's not like a deep faith but
there's a sense that reality holds
together and so similarly when you're
with people in one of these situations
were the logos emergence
that's what I mean by faith reality
holding together or something reality
holds together that there's a and that
we're intimate with reality that it's
not absent from our perception and so
the faith read the reality of other
people for example is what it emerges
when you're gonna dialog us that if we
trust the conversation and trust reason
in our better lights and the care we
have for one another that we'll find the
solution and so it's a faith in humanity
needs you're certain which then and then
I can extend different notes that
everything's gonna work out and be fine
different for the faith that one won't
go to heaven and it requires time too it
requires an unfolding of time it can't
just be rushed or constructed right I'm
covering becoming back to Kairos yeah
yeah I wanted to say how much Zach said
I think he hears again what we're doing
serving we're pulling again we're
pulling apart two notions of faith right
there's a one that was grounded in sort
of you know the emergence of
subjectivity which is the assertion
might be a willful assertion against
evidence which has become a primitive
model whereas kind of faith that Zack is
talking about and I'm talking about tune
especially some of the conversations I'm
having with Jordan Hall is this sense
you know of continuity of contact and
you're not trying to come to closure
what you're trying to do is always
educate right relationship right
relationship isn't a gold state it's
like Keeks does great work on this he
says don't confuse goals with ideals and
I and we even misused the word ideal he
said he complained you know there's a
bull state I'm hungry and I don't want
to be hungry so I can get to a state
that realizes and then I can rest there
right there is ideals are not states of
completion and finality in which you
rest satisfied my ideals are constant
right well they're there they're more
they're there constraint on the manner
of how you do it but honesty isn't a
place I'm trying to get to I can now say
okay I'm done with honesty I don't need
honesty I'm finished it all right I'm
complete honesty isn't instead it's an
ideal it's a whole it's a
a of being in right relationship with
yourself and other people in an ongoing
fashion yeah so there's any completeness
- right it's never completed right you
know like sorry and this just comes to
my mind like Moses never gets to the the
promised land and John the Baptist has
to die before you know it's like we're
all sort of like we're doing something
on faith because it will never realize
that final construction or that's why
not perfection right right that's right
and but ultimately we're we're which
find the the faith is always affording
the emergence precisely because it's
only in the logos of emergence that we
move into post conventionality that we
can be postformal
that we can find the resources to
respond to Kairos it's also that that
the you can't write you can't make it a
goal okay you know 20 minutes in logos
is going to appear in the conversation
that's not gonna happen
that's not gonna happen in fact taking
that stance will kill it right will kill
it completely well it won't chill out it
won't show up sorry Zach you wanted to
say something no I mean I'm I'm really
vibing on it and I'm thinking with the
ideal notion and I'm thinking of Tillich
too in the his notion of idolatry right
just yeah you invest something with
infinite Worth that's not actually
infinite and the proper ideal would be
infinite that you precisely couldn't
achieve it in this life and that's why
you've adopted it as your ideal on some
of the most compelling religious ideals
have that quality like Buddhahood for
example like media which contains a
whole bunch of qualities that you're
unlikely to achieve in this lifetime but
wish you were strong right again even
the love of wisdom for luck finally oh
so Vanya you are always in love with
wisdom because you would never be a god
you would never be perfectly wise right
yeah exactly answer that that it is
infinitely pursuable like asymptotically
throughout life basically it's the
notion of the of the ideal which is you
know very different from other ways of
having motivation and so the question of
how the post conventional identity
his ideal driven wear has many forms of
conventional identity or goal driven is
an important statement and as we know
for most of the happiness research
actually when you meet your goal watch
out because that's when the depression
sets then often people winning gold
medals and and Super Bowls and then get
suicidal afterwards because they
actually did it whereas the ideal is
actually infinitely renewable like
resource of identity construction you
know right it if it in finite game it
right yeah courses you know that follows
up on his previous book the religious
case against belief and you know playing
a finite game versus playing an infinite
game and I think playing in a sense of
serious play game like playing a musical
instrument rather than fooling around or
yeah yeah or jazz where you jazz is a
post formal post conventional thing it
you can't do jazz unless you've done you
have to go through that whole
developmental education or you can't do
it same thing with Chi Chi if you spend
a lot of time getting the form before
you actually start to get the Chi which
is normal which is behind the form yeah
I didn't have to go soon guys I've
already delayed another meeting a bit
but well I think III like what we got to
and I'd like to continue on with but we
were doing a lot of this in we were
exemplifying what I was the discernment
we were trying to get out separating the
good invariants from the bottom various
the wheat from the shaft right and and
and and then how do we educate for that
I think this is the question I'd like to
return to with the two of you guys again
please uh yeah
I always feel this is very unfinished
every time we we do this I feel like
it's because it just keeps going and
going and going and there's just like
I've asked I've only asked about two of
the ten questions that I was thinking of
no yeah no I'm asking you guys so so I'd
be you know I'd be thrilled to keep it
going well I propose we compete we try
to pick up the threads
here and we also try and answer more of
your questions Andrew because I think
they will and they will afford more good
discussion okay I agree thanks thanks so
much thank you Joe it's always good
someday we'll meet in person that would
be really wonderful okay great